At the beginning of 2000, I discovered that my husband was
đầu năm 2000 con phát hiện là chồng con
very addicted to gambling, playing day and night,
rất là mải chơi chơi ngay chơi đêm cơ
gambling, playing cards, nothing was missing.
bác lô đề chơi bài tá lả không thiếu một
After gambling, he would hang out with many
cái gì Chơi xong gào dù với nhiều các
bad friends, then go out at night, drink
bạn xấu ấy xong cũng đi đêm xong uống
alcohol, get drunk, and come home drunk. He would borrow
rượu uống tre say xưa về con cũng đánh
heavily, pay back
đấp con vay nặng lại bốc họ xong trả lại
heavily, and drive a new car. Every place
nặng còn đi xe mói thì hai ba chỗ thì
said that his gambling was due to some kind of spiritual practice, like
toàn bảo rằng là anh ấy chơi bời như thế
opening a
là căn ông Hoà bảy phải Trình Đồng mở
shrine with Hoa, or some kind of fortune-telling ritual, and
Phủ tiễn căn gì cùng Hoà số các kiểu
doing all sorts of things to attract wealth and good luck. He did all sorts of things, but even
xong là mở cùng tài lộc các thứ còn làm
after that, he continued to
đều làm hết sau đó trông con vẫn cứ chơi
gamble even more heavily, without solving
bời nặng hơn nữa không giải quyết được
anything. In 2018, I gave birth to my
một cái gì đến 2018 thì con lại sinh
third child, who had a
thêm cháu thứ ba nữa thì cháu bị chậm
speech delay. I took him to the doctor, and they
nói con đi khám cho cháu thì bác sĩ kết
concluded that he had ADHD (hyperactivity disorder). I've had
luận là cháu bị rối loạn phổ Kỳ tăng
many episodes of this, and it's the worst part. I
động giảm chúi nhiều lần con nng xấu
want to
nhất Con định
escape this life, I don't
thoát Liễu cái cái đời này con không
want to live
muốn sống
anymore. Namo Buddha Shakyamuni.
nữa Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca Mâu Ni
I respectfully greet you, ma'am.
Con kính chào cô ạ Con xin được giới
My name is Vu Thi Nhan, my Dharma name
thiệu tên con là Vũ Thị Nhàn pháp danh
is Nhan Thanh An.  I am currently practicing Buddhism at
là nhàn Thanh Ân con đang tu tập tại Đạo
Minh Quang Buddhist Center, Cau Giay, Hanoi.
Tràng Minh Quang Cầu Giấy Hà Nội chồng
My husband is Nguyen Van Anh, Dharma name Anh Quang
con là Nguễn Văn Anh Pháp danh anh Quảng
Tam. Before I knew about
Tâm ạ trước khi con chưa biết đến phật
Buddhism, and after I learned about Buddhism,
pháp và sau khi con biết đến phật pháp
our family has transformed. My
và gia đình chúng con đã chuyển hóa là
husband has transformed his karma of
chồng con chuyển hóa được nghiệp chơi
gambling, lottery, and betting on football. I
bời cờ bạc lô đề và chắn cạ bóng đá thì
respectfully tell you, we knew each other
con kính Bách cô là chúng con quen nhau
since our youth, but because our backgrounds
là từ thời thanh niên nhưng do hai lng
were different, we got married at the end of 1999.
là khác nhau ạ cuối năm 99 thì chúng con
Then, at the beginning of
được về chung một nhà thì sau đó thì đầu
2000, my husband's parents gave us a separate house. That's when I
2000 thì được bố mẹ chồng cho gi riêng
discovered that my husband was very
con biết là phát hiện là chồng con rất
addicted to gambling, playing day and night, gambling,
là mải chơi chơi ngày chơi đêm cơ B cờ
lottery, and card games – he didn't miss a
bác lô đề chơi bài tá lả không thiếu một
beat. Then in 2001, I gave birth to our
cái gì thì sau đó 2001 thì con sinh cháu
first child, and at that time, my husband was still very addicted to
đầu lòng thì lúc đó thì chồng con mài
gambling, not focusing on work or
chơi lắm không không Tú chí làm ăn và
our child. When our child was
con Đẹ Con đã sinh cháu rồi thì mà lúc
two and a half months old, my husband was still gambling
đó được 2 tháng rưỡi mà chồng con đi
day and night, completely neglecting his
chơi ngày chơi đêm mải chơi không Ờ nhìn
wife and children. He's always been gambling.  At
đến con cái vợ con thì chồng con đi chơi
night,
thì từ trước đến nay là cứ đi đềm thì
I could never sleep. I had to
con không bao giờ con ngủ được Con phải
wait for my husband to come home. I kept thinking about it, and then I
đợi chồng về con cứ nghĩ lo xong con
cried until my eyes were swollen, crying so much that I was sick for
khóc sưng hết cả mắt khóc khóc thậm chí
several days. I carried my
sưng mắt ốm vài ngày Con bế bế cả con
firstborn daughter out at 2:30 in
con gái đầu lòng của con đi đêm lúc 2:30
the morning, and my husband would always
sáng chồng con cũng cứ có lỗi thì lại
apologize, but it was always the same
xin xin lỗi th Đâu Lại Vào Đấy ngựa quen
old story. He kept going out to play
đường cũ thì chồng con cứ đi chơi suốt
like that. Then, in 2003,
như thế thì đến 2003 thì nhân duyên là
I had relatives in Hanoi, and
con có người nhà ở dưới Hà Nội thì các
they told my husband and me to come down to Hanoi to do business.
chú bảo vợ chồng con xuống để làm ăn thì
At that time, my husband and I were washing cars, and he also
lúc đó thì hai vợ chồng con rửa xe thì
took a motorbike taxi
chồng con đi xe ôm thêm bỏ quê xuống Hà
to work in Hanoi. He still went out to play, hanging out with
Nội làm ăn rồi vẫn mài chơi cũng cứ chơi
many bad friends,
xong giao dù mấy nhiều bác các bạn xấu
going out at night, drinking alcohol, getting drunk, and coming home drunk. I would
ấy xong cũng đi đêm xong uống rượu uống
hit him, but I was patient and
tre say xưa về con cũng đánh đắp con con
tried to
thì con nhẫn nhịn con khuyên chồng con
reason with him. Each time, he would just go out and behave himself for about five or fifteen days, then it would be back to square one. He would just keep playing like that, endlessly. I couldn't make any money, I just
thế thì làm ra tiền thì không đề ra được
kept playing.
bà nhiều cả thì cứ chồng con cứ chơi
Then I borrowed money at exorbitant interest rates,
xong rồi vay lãi vay nặng
paying back the high interest
lại bốc họ bốc họ xong trả lãi nặng
many times. Then, during the Tet holiday,
nhiều lần như thế xong những năm mà Tết
at the end of the year, I was always
đến ấ cuối năm mà về nhà ấy còn lúc nào
worried, constantly checking on my husband and children to
còn lo sợ là lúc nào để ý chồng con là
see if they were out gambling. Every Tet, my husband would pawn the
xem có đi chơi không thì chồng con cắm
motorbike, and after
cả xe Tết nào cũng thế cắm xe xong rồi
saving up, I'd
tiết kiệm được thì cũng năm đó thì cũng
buy a
còn mua may hết luôn Mua mua được cái
gold ring to show off. When I
nhẫn vàng ở Tết về đeo thể hiện để chó
came home from Hanoi, during Tet, my
oai ấ từ Hà Nội về thì Tết đến thì như
husband would gamble it away. In the
chồng con cắm cắm để đánh bạc xong những
following years, we'd borrow money again, and then in
những năm tiếp theo vẫn vay tiền hết thì
2008, I gave birth to a
đến năm 2008 thì con lại Sinh được một
second child, a daughter. My husband continued
cháu thứ hai nữa cũng là con gái chồng
gambling like that. I just kept
con vẫn cứ chơi chên biên như thế thôi
enduring it, day after day, month after month, year after year.
qua năm đấ con vẫn cứ chịu nhẫn như thế
Now I'm
giờ con
thinking about the worst possible path. I've thought about
bảo con nghĩ đến con đường xấu nhất ấy
escaping this life, I
định thoát Liễu cái cái cái đời này con
don't want to live anymore. At that time, I was
không muốn sống nữa lúc đó
suffering so much, I didn't know what to do.
thì con khổ quá con không không biết làm
I even thought about dying.  Nothing was
thì con nghĩ là chết thì cũng không giải
resolved, my parents got pregnant and were
quyết cái gì xong bố mẹ mang thai mắc
called dogs. (Uncle, 2009) I was
tiếng chó că chú ở dưới đây 2009 ấ conn
suffering, I didn't
khổ con không
know who to rely on. I was being turned around, so
biết nương tựa vào đầu đ con bị quay ra
I thought about going to
con nghĩ đến con đường là đi xem bói con
fortune tellers. I went to two or three fortune tellers, and they said, "
đi xem bói thì hai ba chỗ thì toà bảo
Ah, my husband is a spirit of Ông Bảy. He's
rằng là à Anh ĩ là căn Ông Bảy anh ấy
playing around like that, so he needs to be cut off. He needs to be a
chơi bơi như thế là cắt ông bày căn ông
medium to open a shrine for him." I
hoang bảy phải Trình Đồng mở Phủ Thế con
believed them, I followed them
tin thu con tin theo luôn
several times, spending
luôn mấy lần tham gia là tiền tốn hàng
millions of dong. Then they opened a shrine for my
và tr triệu đồng Xong tức là mở phủ cho
husband, a shrine, a shrine. Yes, they opened a shrine for him, they cut off his spirit and changed his
chồng ấy à mở phủ à mở phủ rồi Vâng
fate, and
Trình Đồng mở Phủ tiễn căn gì cùng hoàn
then they opened a shrine for wealth and fortune, and
số các kiểu xong là mở cù Tài Lộc các
did everything to pay off all my debts. I owed a
các thứ còn làm đều làm hết nợ
lot of money to the old man. The
gì V già trà nợ Tào Quan nhiều lắm thầy
fortune tellers kept saying whatever they wanted,
bói cứ bảo thế nào thầy C bảo thế nào đ
and I just followed their advice. At that
còn làm theo thế lúc con cứ tâm con cũng
time, I just did
chỉ biết là là như thế thì tại vì lúc
n't know how to do it, but
bấy giờ nó không biết bằng cách nào
they said it would work, so I
người ta bảo là sẽ được thành ra là mình
just followed. Yes, I respectfully ask you,
cứ theo thôi Vâng thế con Kính bạch cô
after that, I still continued to play around and got worse,
là sau đó trông con vẫn cứ chơi bời nặng
and nothing was resolved.
hơn nữa không giải quyết được một cái
Even in old age, sometimes my
gìà Thậm chí còn để đứa con lắm lúc
husband
chồng
comes home drunk, gambling, and doing all sorts of things. It's
con về rượu chè cờ bạc say xìn các kiểu
not just gambling; he goes out
không phải là đánh bạc không đâu Đi chơi
all night, partying until dawn. He's involved with other women,
thâu đêm xốc sáng C laok các thứ còn gái
but I don't see it, I do
gú thì con không nhìn thấy con không
n't suspect anything. I just
không không không nghi ngờ cả con chỉ
know he's out partying like that, and
biết là chồng con đi chơi như thế rồi mà
I'm suffering so much. It cost me hundreds of
con khổ quá thế là tốn hàng vài trăm
millions of dong. Even at 22,
triệu đồng như thế Thế năm 22 thế nhưng
I still endured it
mà cứ theo như thế con vẫn cứ chịu nhẫn
because I still went to fortune tellers, still went to have my bad luck removed, and still went
được tại vì con vẫn cứ đi xem bói vẫn cứ
to other places. My husband kept borrowing money, going to loan sharks, deceiving people. Then in
thứ hết chỗ này đến chỗ khác lừa dối đến
2018, I gave birth to a third child, who
2018 thì con lại sinh thêm cháu thứ ba
had a speech delay. When I took her to
nữa thì cháu bị chậm nói con đi khám cho
the doctor, they concluded she had ADHD (
cháu thì bác sĩ kết luận là cháu bị rối
hyperactivity disorder). It was
loạn phộ Kỳ tăng động giảm chui như thế
so miserable. Two daughters, and a
thì rất là khổ rồi hai đứa con gái mà
husband who just gambles and plays around like that. What can he rely on? All he can do
chồng thì chơi chơi bời như thế cha nhờ
is pay off debts, get
mỗi một cái chuyện đó là được đi trả nợ
scolded by people, and then
được người ta đến người ta mắng và được
pay off debts again. And then in 2018...
đi trả nợ thế rồi đến 2018 thì lại sinh
Having a son and a daughter, and then a
ra con trai con gái lại được cậu con
son, I thought life could turn a new
trai thì nghĩ là cuộc đời có thể sang
page, but it turned into something else entirely.
trang mà nó lại sang một cái trang gì
It's very difficult to reread,
đấy Nó rất là khó đọc lại sức khỏe của
especially with my child's health, right? That page is even
cháu như thế đúng không Đấy là cái trang
more difficult than a husband's gambling addiction, is
lại còn khổ hơn cả Chồng cờ bạc nữa cơ
n't it, my friends? With a gambling husband,
có đúng không các đạio hữu Chồng cờ bạc
I'd say, "Well, if he
thì mình lại còn bảo thôi thì nó có thời
stays, he stays; if not, then I leave," but I
điểm ở thì ở không ở thì bỏ nhưng con
can't abandon my child. And then my child developed autism, so
thì không thể bỏ được mà lại cháu lại
I knew it would be
rơi vào tự kỷ như thế thì mình xác định
a very long and arduous journey. By chance, I was
lại lại một cái vất vả rất là dài con
browsing Facebook and
nhờ nhân duyên là con lướt Facebook và
saw an article about children with autism and
con được xem cái bài viết là trẻ phổ kỷ
speech delays who practice at Ba Vang Temple. They can
chậm nói là tu theo chùa Ba Vàng là à
transform quickly and learn to speak. I told my husband, "Honey,
Được chuyến hóa nhanh biết nói thì còn
I've been following
bảo mới chồ con và anh ơi em theo dõi ở
Ba Vang Temple for many years. We've been
trên chùa Ba Vàng mà nhà mình nhiều năm
going to Ba Vang Temple for many years, even at the beginning of the
cũng về nhà chùa Ba Vàng những cái đầu
year when they were still under construction. We've
năm mà nhà chùa đang xây dựng là chúng
been going since 2014." So I
con về từ năm 2014 rồi Đạ Thế là con mới
told my husband, "That's right," and I clicked on the
bảo chồng con thế TH và con cũng bấm vào
admin page. The admin page
trang quản trị ấy thì trang quản trị
asked me to text them my
trang thì bảo nhắn tin cho con để địa
address and phone number to get
chỉ mấy Số điện thoại để để được thông
information.  More than a year passed, and I didn't have
tin thì con bẵng đi hơn Mộ năm thế là
enough confidence to
con không Không con không đủ tự tin để
write down the address. At that time, I didn't
con con viết số địa chỉ lúc ấy con không
know that temples practiced like this. Now,
biết là chùa tu tập như thế này bây giờ
more than a year later, my
th con bắng đi hơn một năm sau thì cháu
son came back. By then, he was over 4 years old, and he couldn't speak or understand anything anymore. So I started to go back to find him. I went to the website and asked about practicing to transform my son. The website administrators
con trai thì ở ban quản trị trang mới
replied that I should leave my phone number and address so they
trả lời là mình sẽ để lại số điện thoại
could find a
cho ban quản trị sẽ tìm xem là ở cái khu
temple in that area. They
vực đấy có đạo tràng là tu tập không thì
would send me the phone number
ban quản trị Trang sẽ gửi số điện thoại
so I could contact
mình của mình để cho mình tự liên hệ với
them directly to ask for help. But
nhau để nhờ đạo trào Gi giúp đỡ thế Như
now I'm scared. As soon as I went online, they asked for my
bây giờ thì em cũng thấy sợ chứ vừa lên
phone number and address to help. I was
điện thoại cho xin địa chỉ để giúp bng
scared, so I didn't reply, did
Thế là sợ thế là không trả lời không cho
n't give my phone number or address.
số điện thoại cũng không cho địa chỉ thế
More than 15 years have passed, and my son has...  At four
bẵng đi hơn 15 năm thì là con mình đã 4
years old, then over four, I started to
tuổi rồi hơn 4 tuổi thì bắt đầu mới quay
return to the page of the esteemed and arduous medical practice.
trở lại trang quý đại y gian nan thế
At that time, I decided to text. And it worked the
đấy Lúc đó là con quyết định nhắn tin
next day. The
Thế là được hôm sau là được được
Minh Quang Buddhist Center called me. I
à Đạo Tràng Minh Quang thì chị gọi điện
asked, "What's the matter?" I
cho con Thế em bảo thế em có việc gì đấy
told them my son was almost five years old
Bảo kể là con trai của em gần năm tuổi
and still couldn't speak, completely clueless,
rồi mà cháu chưa biết nói gì cả mà không
like a blank sheet of paper. He didn't know anything about urinating or
biết như một tờ giấy trắng đái ỉa ra
defecating. He was so quiet,
quần không biết một cái gì cả Vâng lặng
to the point of not being able to control his
đến mức độ mà không làm chủ được cái
bladder and bowels. I respectfully asked the
việc tiểu tiện đại tiện con Kính bạch cô
teacher if he could urinate or defecate in
là bạn nhà con là có thể là đái luôn ở
one place, without
một chỗ ị luôn ở luôn không biết nhận
any awareness. Yes, on the afternoon of August 7th,
thức gì cả Vâng chiều mùng 7 à tháng 8
2023, the whole Buddhist community went to the temple for study. My
năm 2023 cả đạo Trang về chùa tu học
husband also agreed to let me go. I
chồng con cũng đồng ý cho con về con
had to ask my husband, and the following month he came
phải hỏi chồng con tháng sau là chồng
to the temple with me. After
con về chùa cùng con luôn ạ Con đấy Sau
that, I asked to join the Buddhist center, and the head of the
đó thì con xin vào đạo tràng thì trưởng
center guided me to practice and pray for
đạo tràng hướng dẫn cho con là tu tu cầu
peace first, then
an trước đã xong sau tu
practice repentance and transformation to cultivate karma
tập Sám Hối chuyển hóa để để tu nghiệp
for my son's speech delay,
cho Tu nghiệp chậm nói cho con trai chứ
not to cultivate karma for my husband's gambling addiction.  The problem
không tu nghiệp C bạc ch chồng V chủ yếu
is that my child is slow to speak, and despite the suffering, he
là là nghiệp chậm nói con khổ ý là con
persevered day after day, month after
vẫn nhẫn được ấy ngày qua ngày tháng qua
month, practicing self-discipline and autism. Yes, that
tháng là tu kin nghiệp tự kỷ của con
is, slow speech and inability to control his
vâng tức là chậm nói và không làm chủ
behavior, called autism spectrum disorder,
được hành vi gọi là phổ tự kỷ à rối loạn
attention deficit hyperactivity disorder,
phổ tự kỷ tăng động giảm chú ý dối loạn
or a severe developmental disorder.
phát triển à dối loạn phát triển nặng
Yes, at that time, the doctor diagnosed it like that, and after gradually
thế cơ mà nhỉ Vâng lúc đó thì bác sĩ kê
practicing, after a few months,
dần vào con tu tập thì mấy tháng sau thì
just two months later,
chỉ hai tháng sau rồi tự nhiên con con
he suddenly knew how to pee by himself. "Mom, pee!" he could say. Two months later, he could
nó biết tự đi tè Mẹ ơi tè hai tháng sau
say "Mom, pee!"
nói được Vâng Úi giời Mẹ ơi tè thì cháu
Two months later, he
nói được mẹ ơi Hai tháng sau con cảm
felt it. Before, he couldn't
nhận được thế Lúc trước thì cháu không
speak. He'd
nói được
call his friends, and they'd say he couldn't speak. He'd call them,
hả gọi bạn qu nó nói nó không nói được
but they wouldn't turn their heads.
Vâng gọi gọi được cũng không quay đầu
He'd drop the
lại vâng nó Ngịch tay thả từ cái điện
phone from the fifth floor, shattering it.
thoại từ trên tầng năm xuống vỡ tan cái
But after only two months of practicing, he could speak and say "
điện thoại thế mà tu có hai tháng mà nói
Mom!". No mistake, in just two months, he
được còn gọi được mẹ ơi Không nói sai có
suddenly said "Mom!"
ha tháng tự nhiên gọi mẹ ơi
And he felt that he was transforming month by month,
và cháu con cảm nhận là cháu chuyển hóa
month by month. From the first
từng tháng một từng tháng Một đến tận
two months until now, he's been...
bây giờ thì cái hai lúc hai tháng đó còn
The days have come, and there are still months left, and my
từ ngày đến giờ là còn tháng nào còn về
husband and children are all here, not a single month is missing. So,
cả chồng con không có thiếu tháng nào cả
how is my child doing now? Now he knows how to go to the
thế nào rồi giờ là cháu biết tự tự đi vệ
toilet by himself, he knows his wishes and what he wants
sinh tự đi tè giờ biết mong muốn của
from others, meaning he can
mình với mọi người rồi à tức là tương
interact now. Yes, Mom, I need to pee. Mom,
tác được rồi Vâng Mẹ ơi con đi tề Mẹ ơi
I need to drink water. I press the elevator button to go up to the floor to drink. I go
con uống nước lên bấm thang máy lên tầng
up and drink, I know how to open
mà uống cháu lên cháu uống biết căn mở
the tap and write. He's developing, I feel,
vòi mà viếtc cháu phát triển cảm thấy
I feel in a miraculous way. So
con cảm thấy một cách ki Diệu Thế thì
what else is there to do about the transformation? My son,
chuyển viến quá làm gì nữa con của con
my son, has these pictures after I
con trai của con được có những cái bức
practiced repentance and
hình này là sau khi con tu tập sám hối
transformation so that my son could be
chuyển hóa để con trai con được chuyển
transformed like this. Ah, transformed here,
hóa như thế này ạ À được chuyển hóa đây
here, I'm showing this to you all, dear fellow
ở đây tâm chếu CN quán giơ cho các quý
practitioners.
đạo hữu xem nhá này bệnh rối loạn phổ tự
This child had ADHD, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, and now
mà đến bây giờ cháu này Các Đạ ý nhìn
he can draw like this and write properly,
này đó cháu đã vẽ được thế này rồi viết
both in Vietnamese and English.
cả tiếng Việt cả tiếng Anh luôn đấy thế
This is what you call being on the path, that's
này thì gọi là trên con đường là là quá
amazing, isn't it? He's been practicing for 17
giỏi rồi đấy phải không Đấy tu được 17
months.  My grandson, who was once so young,
tháng mà cháu nó từ một đứa trẻ như thế
now knows how to write in both English and
mà bây giờ biết biết viết cả tiếng Anh
Vietnamese, and can draw. Is
tiếng Việt biết vẽ quý đạo hữu thấy giỏi
n't he amazing, so incredibly talented? What is
chưa quá giỏi luôn rất là giỏi phải
Duy drawing? What shape is this? A
không Duy đang vẽ hình gì đây Hình gì
square? A square? What shape is this? A circle? A circle? What shape is this? A rhombus?
Hình vuông hình vuông hình gì đây tròn
What number is he drawing? Three?
quay ra lấy cái gì thôi là cào rách và
Three? So talented! I'd like to add to what you said,
mặt con hay là ví dụ các đạo tr các đạo
Duy, that when Duy first came to the temple with his mother, he exhibited behaviors like hitting people. For example, if his mother just turned to get something, he would scratch her face. Or, for example, if other monks or nuns came to Duy's house, he would
hữu mà đến nhà chợ Duyên ấ là cháu cũng
hit their children.
đánh đánh con của các đạo hữu hay như
But in the last few months, he's
nào đấy nhưng mà mấy tháng nay thì cháu
changed quite a lot. I
cũng thay đổi cũng khá là nhiều ạ cô ạ
think he's
Cháu chuyển hóa tháng nào con thấy
transformed a lot. Anyway, I
chuyển hóa hay qu nhỉ thôi thế bây giờ
'm happy now. Actually,
là vui rồi TH Thực ra là cái bệnh tự kỷ
this autism spectrum disorder with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD)
phổ tự kỷ mà giảm chú ý tăng động này ấy
is very difficult to transform. Although
là rất là khó có thể chuyển hóa Tuy rằng
there's intervention, the
can thiệp 11 một đấy nhưng mà nó tác
effect isn't significant; the percentage of improvement isn't enough.  It's important to
dụng cũng không được là bao nhiêu cái số
know that
phần trăm mà để trở trở nên biết nhận
recognizing and interacting with others is very difficult.
biết trở nên biết tương tác là rất khó
Therefore, the family should continue to practice diligently
thế cho nên là gia đình hãy nỗ lực tu
so that the child can progress
tập tiếp để mà cho cháu đ đã tiến được
to the point of being able to manage
lên đến cái bước là tự làm chủ được việc
hygiene independently, which is very difficult.
vệ sinh là cái chuyện rất là khó rồi
Then, being able to speak is even more difficult, and being
xong lại còn biết nói là khó thứ nữa lại
able to interact with you is also a
còn biết tương tác với mình thì nó đang
sign of development. So,
trên đà phát triển cho nên chúng ta hãy
if we are trying for one year, we should increase our
Nếu mà đang cố gắng năm thì tăng lên
efforts to ten because at this
thành cố gắng 10 bởi vì là cái tuổi nó
young age, the child is truly in the
còn nhỏ này là thực sự ra nó l nó trong
golden age. That means there is still room for development. If we wait too
tuổi vàng Đấy tức là cái còn phát triển
long, it will not
được mình để đến lâu quá là nó sẽ không
develop further, even though
phát triển được tuy rằng lúc bấy giờ
we are just starting to practice now. The merit at
chúng ta mới tu nhưng mà cái Phước lúc
that time cannot transform
bấy giờ nó không thể nào mới chuyển hóa
the body anymore because
được cái cái cái cái cơ thể nữa bởi vì
the body is still
cái Cơ thể lúc đấy nó đang trên đà phát
developing. So, husband and wife should try their best to
triển cho nên là vợ chồng hãy cố gắng để
help the child return to normal
cho cháu nó làm sao trở lại bình thường
when he/she is 67 years old. We must make even
khi mà cháu nó năm 67 tuổi mình phải nỗ
greater efforts, like before, that other person whose
lực cố gắng hơn nữa như là lúc trước cái
child also had autism. The husband and
ấy con bạn ấy cũng tự kỷ này bạn hai vợ
wife practiced for only two or three months,
chồng bạn tu đâu có hai ba tháng gì đấy
but the child still...  When my child was one and a half years old,
nhưng mà cháu nó còn có tuổi rưỡi thì
they practiced and quickly attained enlightenment.
cháu nó tu nó danh nhanh chuyển đế bây
Now, my child is four and a half to five years
giờ con nh mình những bốn tuổi rưỡi năm
old and only just beginning to practice. So we have to make more effort.
tuổi mới tu Thế thì mình phải nỗ lực hơn
The older they get, the harder it becomes. Therefore, my
nữa càng lớn thì lại càng khó cho nên
husband and I must increase our efforts now, making our
bây giờ là vợ chồng phải tăng cái sự cố
child the goal to
gắng này lên nhá lấy con là mục đích để
achieve. Otherwise, we will pass this age, this
đạt được chứ nếu không thì qua cái tuổi
golden time
cái thời gian này gọi là thời gian vàng
for cultivation and transformation, and then our
của tuổi này để mà tu tập chuyển hóa thì
efforts might
khi sự cố gắng nó chuyển sang cái Phước
only lead to other blessings, not
khác thôi chứ nó không thể vào cái Phước
this one anymore. So we must try harder, focus our efforts on
này được nữa cho nên phải cố gắng nỗ lực
cultivating
hơn nữa tập trung vợ chồng dồn vào tu
for our child, dedicating the merit to them. I will
cho cháu nhá hồi hướng cho cháu để con
also tell you more about how my cultivation for my child's karma
lại kể thêm con tu tập cho cho nghiệp
will change my husband and children. When I
thì lại thay đổi chồng con rất là
cultivate, I
là là thay đổi ch mình tu tập thì mình
change my husband and children, and
thay đổi cho chồng cho con rồi chồng
during that time, I continue
được thay đổi trong thời gian đó thì con
cultivating for
tu tập cho
my child. I always wish to
con của con thì con vẫn Lúc nào con mong
dedicate the merit to my husband so that he will
nguyện là hồi hướng cho chồng của con là
stop gambling, not associate with
bớt chơi cờ bạc này không chơi với bạn
bad friends, and not meet bad people to
xấu không gặp những người bạn xấu để
socialize with, so that my
chơi bời giao du với xã hội như thế để
child can be better off.  My suffering was so overwhelming, I only knew to tell the
cho con được bướt khổ con chỉ biết bạch
Buddha that.
Phật như thế thôi trong
Then, my husband, due to some karmic cause, had kidney stones. He had
thì sau đó thì chồng con nhân duyên là
kidney stones for
chồng con bị soi thận ấy soi thận mà bị
many years, for many years, and then in one
nhiều năm rồi s năm s năm rồi có có một
year, he had kidney stones twice. The
năm mà chồng conn tán sỏi hai lần thế
last time, due to some karmic cause, he
lần cuối cùng là nhân duyên là chồng con
had this problem, and I was practicing meditation. So I
bị như thế thì con đang tu tập Thế là
shared with my husband, "
con mới chia sẻ cho chồng con là đấy anh
Look at those videos, the Buddhist practitioners
xem những cái video đấy các phật tử tu
at Ba Vang Temple, they're transforming themselves. You have to
theo chùa Bá vng ấy người ta chuyển hóa
have the truth to be able to speak it out."
phải có sự thật mới nói lên được lên
So I asked the fellow practitioners
thành lời thế là con nhờ các đạo hữu ở
in the temple to
trong đạo tràng là sách thấn chồng con
guide my husband so he could
để cho chồng
practice meditation. Now my husband can tell
con tu tập giờ chồng thì có thể kể
stories about his practice, his experiences, and
chuyện về chồng tu tập kinh nghiệp giờ
how he's doing with gambling now. Respectfully, my name
cờ bạc thế nào rồi Kính bạch cô con tên
is Nguyen Van Anh. My wife
là Nguyễn Văn Anh Anh Quảng tâm thì vợ
practiced meditation for our son first, and then she
con tu cái nghiệp trước cho con trai của
went with the other
con xong thì con vợ con cứ đi cùng các
practitioners to the temple, and I followed along. At
đạo hữu về chùa thì con cũng đi theo lúc
that time, I didn't think about practicing anything;
ấy con chưa nghĩ gì con tu tập gì cả thì
my wife was just practicing for our son. I
vợ con chỉ là tu tập cho con tr của con
told her, "What are you doing? Just do what you're doing. You practice, you
thôi thì con cũng bảo thự em làm gì Em
practice, I'm not
cứ làm em C tu em C tu anh không liên
involved."  It's not related at all. Then, after
quan không Cái gì Kệ Chả liên quan gì
a while, I kept following fellow
đâu nhá Thế xong một thời gian con cứ đi
practitioners to the temple. Every month, on the 18th
theo các đạo hữu về chùa tháng nào con
day of the lunar month, I would go to the temple. Then, I got
cũng ngày mùng tá còn về chùa thế là con
kidney stones, and for
xong con bị à bị bị à thậ đau sỏi thận
many years, I had them removed. After that,
nhiều năm thế là con đi tán sỏi về xong
other fellow practitioners encouraged me to pray for
được các khác đạo ữu xách tấn cho con là
peace and well-being, to heal my body and soul. I followed their advice and practiced.
cầu An Tu cầu An là để là cho cái cái
But during that time, I was just
Nhưng mà con trong cái lúc ấy là con vẫn
practicing; I hadn't thought about anything else. I was still
gọi là cứ tu thôi con chưa có nghĩ gì
gambling. I gambled so much that I
vẫn chơi mà vẫn chơi cờ bạc con chơi cờ
hid it from my
bạc mà đến nỗi con chôi giấu chôi Giấu
wife and children. I even lost money. When
vợ con đến lỗi con có thể con thua lúc
my wife trusted me,
kh vợ con Lại tin tưởng con là con cầm
she would take the money and
tiền thì con lại cầm tiền con Mẫn chơi
gamble secretly. After a few more months, I was
con chơi giấu xong một vài tháng nữa thế
encouraged a lot, and I
là con cácc là sách tấn rất nhiều th bắt
started practicing repentance and repentance,
đầu con vào con tu bài sám hối sám hối
starting to repent and clear my wrong views. From that
bắt đầu nghiệp Tà kiến của con thế là từ
time, I listened to my master's Dharma teachings, which
lúc ý con được nghe sư phụ giảng pháp cô
purified my karma. I listened and felt that my
sạch pháp nhiều con nghe con cảm thấy là
karma was being cleared.  The gambling was so heavy that
cái nghiệp con quán nặng thế là con đến
I felt I should quit. So I started practicing asceticism.
lúc con cảm thấy là con nên sứt bỏ Thế
Naturally, even now, I do
là con tu thế Tự nhiên đến bây giờ con
n't know what it was like before. Now, I'm asking for
cũng không biết là như thế nào nữa đến
guidance from Buddhist teachings to help me achieve
bây giờ để con hay là phật pháp cho
enlightenment, to
những cái để con giác ngộ được để con
understand, to practice, and to spread the message about
hiểu để con tu tập mà con truyền hóa mọi
gambling. Now I don't think about it anymore.
cờ bạc con Bây giờ con không nghĩ đến
Before, when I gambled, I thought
mọi mà lúc Con trước Con chơi Con nghĩ
about my mistakes, like how I had to look at the lottery numbers at 6 o'clock to
con đến lỗi giờ đến giờ 6 giờ phải dở
see what numbers were drawn, or to see
Xem nay có đề con gì để xem để soi hay
what numbers to bet on tomorrow.
là mê ngủ đánh con gì mê ngủ mê mê ngủ
Usually,
để mai đánh con gì Thường thường người
people gamble to win. Even when I was practicing asceticism and praying for peace, I
ta là m để đánh đề Kể cả lúc tu cầu an
still gambled, I gambled secretly,
con vẫn chơi con chơi con chơi giấu
but before I gambled a lot, when I was practicing asceticism and praying for
nhưng mà ngày trước con chơi nhiều đến
peace, I gambled less, only
lúc tu cầu an chơi ít con chu chơi chỉ
a few million dong, but before I gambled
mấy triệu thôi nhưng lúc trước Con chơi
a lot. Then I started practicing card games and numbers. And then,
rất nhiều Xong đến tu bài số tá Thế là
naturally, I gradually stopped paying attention
con tự nhiên con dần dần con không để ý
to everything. I stopped
đến gì cái Mọi sự về đến V chơi vời mà
associating with bad friends. Bad friends
con không giao du bạn xấu nữa bạn xấu có
might try to tempt me, but I would avoid them. Gradually, I stopped,
thể là rủ con đ con sẽ né con né Dần con
but only for a short time. I would go home, I
cũng ra nhưng con chỉ một lúc con đi về
would go home first. That's how it was from that moment on.  I've
con sẽ đi về trước C không Thế là từ lúc
transformed everything, everything
ấy con chuyền hóa được mọi thứ mọi thứ
is gambling. I see alcohol, and I don't
là cờ bạc con thấy rượu con cũng không
drink it anymore, unlike before. My addiction has decreased so much that
uống mới như ngày trước C giảm rất nhiều
many people say, "This guy
đến nỗi nhiều người ta bảo thằng này
must be crazy," or "It's just that he's suddenly like this." He's the
chắc này dở th nào ấy bảo là tự nhiên n
kind of person who refuses any invitation to do anything. When I
mọi thấy nó Nó kiểu gì mà rủ cái gì nó
go back to my hometown, everyone
cũng không Chứ đi về quê các mọi người
gambles, and sometimes I drink
cứ chơi cờ bạc con nhiều lúc con uống VT
alcohol, but I avoid going to other places so I don't get
chá rượu con đi né chỗ khác để con không
involved in that anymore. I
Con không bị dính và cái đấy nữa đấy Con
truly believe in the Three
thực sự đ con cũng thực sực là chiên tam
Jewels, the Master, the Great Nun, and the Head of the
bảo chiên sư phụ cũng đại ni và C chủ
Dharma. They have given me very good Dharma teachings that helped me to awaken and let go of everything. I respectfully ask the Head of the Dharma, my name is Tran Thi Truc Dao, my Dharma name is Dao Huong Doan. I was assigned by the Dharma center to
Hương Đoan ạ thì con được đạo tràng phân
guide Brother Anh in his practice.
công là hướng dẫn cho anh Anh tu tập thì
Initially, before guiding Brother
ban đầu trước khi tu hướng dẫn cho đạo
Anh in his practice, I saw on his
hữu Anh tu tập thì con cũng xem ở trên
Facebook that he was always
Facebook của đạo hữu anh thì con thấy là
going out and having fun, going to temples
đi đi chơi rồi là đi Tức là đi đền Phủ
and other places, going a lot of places. And
rồi các thứ là đi rất là nhiều mà đi thì
from
toàn đi đi con tức là theo theo cái cái
my perspective, it was just socializing and going
nhìn nhận của con thì là cũng đi giao du
out.  With friends, he interacts with
rồi đi với bạn bè mà Giao lưu với cả bạn
bad friends, the kind of gangster friends, and I
xấu bạn kiểu bạn giang hồ ấy thế và con
know that, well, my friend, he drinks
cũng biết là ờ đạo hữu anh thì cũng uống
alcohol and is hot-tempered, and he
rượu và nóng tính rồi cũng hay hay nọ
often curses and scolds his wife. Sometimes, his wife,
hay như là chửi vợ mắng vợ và nhiều khi
Ms. Nhan, calls him,
thì ờ chị Nhàn thì cũng có gọi điện cũng
crying and telling him stories, saying how much he
khóc khóc rồi cũng kể rất là cũng rất là
loves her.
thương
Then, my friend had the opportunity to follow his
thì sau đó thì đạo hữu anh thì được nhân
wife to the temple to
duyên là vào đi theo vợ về về chùa để
look after the children so that he could practice Buddhism.
trông con để cho đạo hữu nhà tu tập thế
Now, my friend, he's only doing it
V bây giờ là đạo hữu anh chẳng qua chỉ
for the sake of his children. Yes, and he's also following me,
vì con thôi Vâng và cũng là đi theo tôi
but he doesn't intend to join a Buddhist
cũng chưa có ý định là vào đạo tràng tu
practice center yet. My friend, you have the
tập ạ Đạo Hữu có được đạo tràng là hướng
guidance of the Buddhist practice center to practice repentance and transformation, to
dẫn là tu sám hối chuyển hóa
transform your karma and wrong views
để để để chuyển hóa cái nghiệp mà tà
because you've been going to spirit mediums,
kiến của đạo hữu bởi vì đạo hữu là đi
opening shrines, gambling, and
Hầu Đồng mở Phủ rồi đi chơi lô đề cờ bạc
while practicing, listening to Dharma
rồi là ờ trong khi mà tu tập Nghe Pháp
or doing your duties, you
hay là làm phận sự thì đạo hữu là cũng
still have things that aren't going as
cũng vẫn còn những cái mà chưa được như
planned. During your practice, the Buddhist practice
ý ạ trong thời gian mà đạo hữu tu tập
center has guided you to
thì đạo tràng cũng có hướng dẫn là đạo
practice, listen to scriptures and Dharma, and
hữu là tu tập và nghe kinh thính pháp và
practice according to the chapters.  The club's program
ờ tu tập theo các chương trình của câu
means that there's a program that
lạc bộ tức là có chương trình nà là cứ
encourages fellow practitioners to participate in
Khuyến tấn là đạo hữu là cứ tham gia tu
practice because both of you have a lot of free
tập hết bởi vì hai đạo hữu là rất là có
time at home. And while you're
nhiều thời gian ở nhà đấy ạ và thế trong
practicing, the
thời gian mà Ờ đạo hữu Anh tu tập thì ờ
community also has many responsibilities,
đạo tràng cũng có ờ nhiều những cái phận
such as helping
sự trong đạo tràng như là đi giúp đỡ các
families set up practice groups or
gia đình khai đàn tu tập hoặc là các cái
other responsibilities within the community. That is,
phận sự khác ở trong đạo tràng Tức là
during your practice, you
trong trong thời gian tu tập là đạo hữu
've experienced changes, and you've been
có những cái chuyển biến mà ờ và Đạo Hữu
very diligent in your practice. As a result, you
tu tập cũng rất là chăm chỉ và từ đó thì
don't have time to be
Đạo Hữu Bảo cũng không có thời gian để
influenced or lured by bad friends. I
mà và cũng bạn bè xấu lôi kéo hay Rủ dây
see that
là đạo hữu cũng không có đi con thấy là
during your practice, you've experienced
trong tu tập thì cũng có những chuyển
very positive changes. You
biến rất là tích cực và đạo hữu cũng
no longer gamble or play lottery, and you're very
không còn chơi lô đề cờ bạc và cũng rất
happy to help everyone in the
là hoan hỉ giúp đỡ mọi người ở trong đạo
community. Dear fellow practitioners, it's
tràng Kính thưa quý Đạo Hữu ở đây thì
true that
đúng là gia đình
your family is in a very
của đạo hữu là cũng rơi vào cái cảnh rất
difficult situation. You and your wife are gambling and playing games, and you
khổ mình thì chơi bời cờ bạc hai vợ
earn money,
chồng làm như thế cũng gọi là có tiền
but...  The way I played, I
đấy nhưng mà mình chơi thành ra là mình
didn't save much, but the
không để ra được bao nhiêu nhưng cái
important thing is the mental anguish.
quan trọng nữa là cái cái nỗi đau tinh
Then, when the baby was born,
thần thế rồi đến khi đẻ ra cậu bé thì
he wasn't born as he wished. So
cậu bé lại cũng không được nhĩ ý thế thì
here, we have to understand that from the beginning, the
ở đây chúng ta phải thấy rằng là từ đầu
wife suffered, but she had to love the
là vợ thì khổ đấy nhưng mà phải thương
child first. So the wife practiced Buddhism for the child, and then the
con trước cho nên là vợ cũng tu cho con
husband also went to the temple. That's how
xong chồng vì thế mà cũng về chùa cho
the blessings came from. The husband and
nên cái Phước báo nó sinh ra từ đấy vợ
wife had to create conditions for the wife because of her
chồng cũng phải tạo điều kiện cho vợ vì
love for the child, and that's how the blessings came
thương con tro nên cái Phước báo nó sinh
from. Then later, the husband also practiced Buddhism, and
ra từ đấy thế rồi về sau chồng cũng tu
because of the blessings he had,
nữa thì do cái Phước báo của mình nó có
his preferences
cho nên là cái sở thích của mình nó thay
changed. Firstly, when you have karmic consequences and
đổi thứ nhất là khi mình có nghiệp báo
you have no wealth, your
là mình không có tài sản thì mình Sở
preferences are only to do things that will consume
thích là chỉ làm những cái việc khiến
all your wealth. That's how it is in this world, our
cho cho hết tài sản thôi trên đời này
karma.
lại như thế đấy cái nghiệp của chúng ta
That's why the Buddha taught us:
mà thế cho nên Đức Phật mới dạy chúng ta
wealth goes out through seven
này tài sản đi ra bằng bảy cửa bằng bảy
doors: first,
cửa cửa thứ nhất đó
sickness and disease; second, evil children destroying things;
là ốm đau bệnh tật thứ hai là con ác tàn
third, officials; fourth, theft and
phá thứ ba là quan lại thứ tư là trộm
robbery; fifth, rebellion; and
cướp Thứ năm là giặc
sixth, the death of high-ranking officials.  The seventh point
rã thứ sáu là quan đại tịch thu thứ bảy
is that uncontrolled gambling and other frivolous activities
chính là các cái việc chơi bời mà chúng
lead to
không kiểm soát được khiến nó mất mát
financial losses. This is considered the
tài sản thì cái này nó thuộc về cái
karma of losing one's possessions. The
nghiệp thất thoát tài sản của mình Mình
suffering comes from not having possessions, which is why
không có được tài sản đau khổ cho nên là
we have this habit. All
ta có cái sở thích đó tất cả những người
gamblers and frivolous people initially
chơi bời cờ bạc thì từ đầu người ta là
just enjoy it,
chỉ ham ham thích thích bình thường thôi
but later they become addicted to it. This is called
nhưng về sau người ta say rồi gọi là say
gambling addiction in Buddhism, a karmic consequence of
mê cờ bạc cá độ là say mê thì cái đấy
gambling addiction. Therefore,
cái nghiệp là ham mê cờ bạc cho nên đến
when we practice Buddhism and take refuge in the
khi mình tu tập Phật pháp thì mình quy y
Three Jewels, we must end this karma. Karma is the
Tam Bảo là phải chấm dứt cái nghiệp này
process of
nghiệp là những cái tiến trình trong suy
thinking, speaking, and doing. It's called
nghĩ lời nói V việc làm thì gọi là
bodily karma, verbal karma, and
nghiệp thôi gọi là thân nghiệp khẩu
mental karma. So, when a practitioner
nghiệp Ý nghiệp thế thì khi mà đạo ữu tu
cultivates in this way, good karma
tập như thế thì cái thiện nghiệp nó tăng
increases while bad karma decreases. It's
trưởng lên thì cái nghiệp ác nó giảm đi
like having a child who is
cũng giống như mình có một đứa con ấy Nó
unfilial; gradually,
bất hiếu thì dần dần những cái hành vi
their filial behavior increases, and their
có hiếu của nó mà tăng thì cái hành vi
unfilial behavior decreases. This is also a
bất hiếu sẽ giảm thì đây cũng là cái kết
result of practice, called the two in one.  One or two
quả tu tập gọi là hai trong một hai cái
karmic sufferings, when practiced together, can be
nghiệp khổ cùng một lần tu nó được
transformed, right? Although the wife practices
chuyển hóa có phải không Tuy rằng vợ tu
for the children, she must also remember her husband.
cho con nhưng cũng phải nhớ đến chồng
Although the husband practices for the children,
Tuy rằng chồng có tu cho con th nhưng mà
during the process, I also think that I am
trong quá trình mình cũng nghĩ mình hỗ
supporting my wife's practice for the children, so my karma
trợ cho vợ tu cho con thì cái nghiệp của
also changes.
mình nó cũng chuyển cái tâm hỗ trợ của
My supportive mindset is the mind of practice. My mind rejoices in the
mình chính là tâm tu cái tâm mình tùy hỉ
practice of others, supporting others in their practice—that is cultivating virtue.
việc tu củaở người khác hỗ trợ cho người
Therefore, thanks to cultivating
Thiện cho nên chính nhờ tu Thiện đấy là
virtue, you have helped
đạo Hữu đã giúp chính đạo hữu để có thể
yourself to transform, and your habits have
mình chuyển hóa được và cái sở thích của
changed. You feel
mình nó thay đổi chên đạo hữu thấy như
like you have been freed from something that was
là mình cởi ra được khỏi một cái cái gì
binding you, right?
đó chói buộc mình có phải không Nhiều
Sometimes you
lúc là mình cảm thấy thật sự là lúc
feel like
không đạo hữu đấy Nhiều lúc cảm thấy như
that. So today, the
thế Thế thì hôm nay thì đúng là phật
Buddha's teachings are truly wondrous. In
pháp rất là Vi Diệu ở trong câu lạc bộ
our club, there are some guys who used to gamble and play the
của chúng ta thì có những anh gọi như là
lottery, but after practicing, they have become Dharma
lô đề cờ bạc sau khi tu tập đã trở thành
center leaders. They have become Dharma center leaders.
đạo tràng trưởng rồi đấy thành đ trang
For example, at the Tay Tuu Dharma center, there
trưởng rồi đấy như ở đạo tràng Tây Tựu
are several Dharma center leaders who are
là có mấy người đạo tràng trưởng đều là
all...  They were gamblers and drunkards to
toàn là những tay cờ bạc rượu trè mà đến
the point that they were on the police's blacklist,
nỗi mà vào sổ đen của công an phường
constantly under surveillance, and
suốt ngày phải đi theo dõi mà đến bây
now they've all become Buddhist leaders.
giờ là trở thành đạo tràng trưởng hết
So, this is what you call a
rồi đấy Thế thì ở đây là một cái sự gọi
resurrection, isn't it? A
là cải tử Hoàn sinh chứ còn gì nữa phải
resurrection means that we've let
không cải tử Hoàn Sinh tức là mình đã
go of our inherent goodness, and now
chết đi cái tính Thiện của mình bây giờ
our goodness is revived. Is
Cái tính Thiện của mình nó được sống dậy
n't that a resurrection?
thế có phải là cải tử Hoàn sinh không
And especially for the child, the
thế và cả nhất là con nữa Thế ở đây thì
couple should try harder. First,
vợ chồng hãy cố gắng hơn nữa bước đầu
congratulations to the family for
cũng là chúc mừng cho gia đình đã vượt
overcoming two calamities. The first is a very
qua được hai cái nạn Nạn đây là nạn rất
painful calamity: the husband's gambling addiction, and the
khổ nạn về chồng lô đề cờ bạc và nạn thứ
second is the child's attention deficit
hai là rối loạn phổ tự kỷ giảm chú ý của
hyperactivity disorder (ADHD). This is very
con tăng động giảm chú ý là cái này rất
difficult. Now we've come
là khó thế Bây giờ chúng ta đã đi được
60-70 minutes on our son's path.
đến 6 70 ph con đường của con trai rồi
We will continue further, focusing our minds and
mình sẽ tiếp tục đi thêm nữa tâm chế
believing that he will transform from
quán tin rằng nó sẽ phải chuyển nó từ
nothingness to existence, from existence to cessation, from existence to existence,
không còn trở thành có còn có thì trở
until
thành hết có là có chuyển nghiệp đến lúc
we reach the point where all karma is gone for
mà chúng ta sẽ đi đến chỗ hết nghiệp cho
him, because at his age he can still practice.
cháu vì cái tuổi là của cháu vẫn tu được
Through this, I also ask all fellow
nhá Thế thì qua đây thì cũng xin
practitioners in our community to try our
hữu trong đạo tràng chúng ta hãy cố gắng
best in our practice. Those who are still in
hãy cố gắng tu tập Ai còn có những cái
difficult circumstances, many practitioners
hoàn cảnh khổ ấy thì nhiều đạo hữu thì
have this situation: many practice for a
có cái thế này nhiều đạo hữu mình tu một
while, and when they don't see their karma
thời gian mình không thấy nghiệp của
change, they become discouraged. But
mình chuyển thì mình chán nản nhưng mà
what good does discouragement do? Because
mình chán nản thì được cái gì đâu bởi vì
before practicing, their karma was already like
lúc trước mình chưa tu thì nghiệp nó như
this. Now, when
thế này rồi Thế bây giờ ở đây là khi mà
we want to practice, for example, if the whole family practices together,
mình muốn tu thì ví dụ như cả nhà ta
it will be faster. If we practice alone, it will be slower. And
phải dồn vàoo tu thì nó nhanh còn nhà
if we practice alone and
nếu như nhà mình lại có một mình mình tu
some people hinder us, it will take even
xong lại vài người cản mình thì nó lại
longer. Therefore, let's
còn phải lâu nữa Thế cho nên là chúng ta
persevere in our practice because this is the
hãy kiên trì tu bởi vì đây là con đường
only path; there is no other way.
duy nhất rồi không cò con đường nào khác
Even if our husbands gamble, that
rồi chúng ta thì kể cả chồng đi cờ bạc
disease can be cured. Parents
cái bệnh đấy làm gì hay chữa được cha mẹ
advise, siblings advise,
thì cũng khuyên anh em thì cũng khuyên
good friends advise,
bạn tốt thì cũng khuyên khuyên hết rồi
but there is one thing we
thế nhưng mà chỉ còn một cái chúng ta
must understand: karma. Therefore, it is
phải hiểu nó là nghiệp nữa cho nên bắt
essential that our loved ones
buộc những người thân của chúng ta phải
practice so that we can transmit the message. For example...
tu thì mình mới có thể truyển được ví dụ
As a wife, she essentially has to
như là bạn vợ là bạn ấy coi như là phải
endure all the suffering caused by her husband,
chịu hết những cái nỗi khổ do chồng gây
so she practices to
ra cho nên là bạn ấy tu bạn ấy chuyển
transform her karmic suffering. Because she has to endure her
hóa cái nghiệp khổ của mình là phải chịu
husband's suffering, her husband must also transform.
chịu chồng như thế thì chồng phải chuyển
So, when one person practices,
thôi đấy cho nên là một người tu thì một
another person is transformed. This is very
người nữa được chuyển cái này nó rất là
beneficial, and this is the miraculous power
lợi ích và đây chính là cái sự linh diệu
in Buddhism. This is very
trong Phật pháp cái này là rất là linh
miraculous and difficult to comprehend. In Buddhism,
diệu rất là khó thể nghĩ bản trong Phật
two husbands and wives like this, so please try your
pháp hai vợ chồng như thế cho nên hãy cố
best. I also wish all fellow practitioners diligence and
gắng nhé cũng chúc các quý đạo hữu tinh
joyful participation in the Dharma assembly. Each
tấn tùy hỉ ban cắn sự đạo tràng nhé mỗi
person is a messenger of the Tathagata. First,
người là một sứ giả của Như Lai thứ nhất
as a messenger, you go to the Tathagata's house to
là sứ giả thì tự đi đến nhà như lai để
learn, and then bring the knowledge
học xong sau đó thì mang các kiến thức
of the Tathagata's house (the Three Jewels) to
của nhà Như Lai nhà Như Lai là tam bảo
everyone. Dear fellow practitioners,
đấy đến cho mọi người thưa các quý đạo
having received the blessings of the Buddha's teachings,
hữu được được Ân hưởng giáo pháp của
please transmit them to
Phật thì hãy truyển Tải đến cho mọi
everyone, just like I said. This is
người giống như em nó phát biểu đây là
true: in my heart, when I feel that my
thật là trong tâm mình mình thấy mình
suffering has ended, I truly love
hết khổ rồi mình mới thật sự thương
those around me. That's why I ask, "
những người bên cạnh mình cho nên cứ bảo
Why are the Buddhists of the Golden National Club so
Tại sao Phật tử câu lạc bộ Quốc vàng
enthusiastic?" Because the Buddhists of the
nhiệt tình thế bởi vì Phật tử câu lạc bộ
Golden National Club are all...  People who suffer come to
Quốc vàng toàn những người khổ đến phật
Buddhism and are transformed. When I
pháp được chuyển hóa đến lúc mình nhìn
see the person next to me is just like me,
thấy người bên cạnh cũng giống mình cho
I want them to also know about
nên là mình mong muốn họ cũng biết đến
Buddhism, so I enthusiastically follow it.
phật pháp cho nên mình nhiệt tình thôi
This enthusiasm is simply
cái sự nhiệt tình chính là cái sự đồng
empathy, okay? Anyway, I wish all fellow
cảm thôi mà nhá Thôi chúc các quý đạo
practitioners good spirits. And I also hope that
hữu tinh thấn nha Thế và cũng mong rằng
all fellow practitioners who see
tất cả các đạo hữu nào xem được cái câu
this story of Karma Transformation will
chuyện Chuyển Nghiệp này thì các quý đạo
strive to diligently
hữu cũng cố gắng tinh tấn
learn from the practitioners here to practice.
học các đạo hữu ở đây để mà tu đấy Đạo
This fellow practitioner even practices nine times a day, observing the eight precepts
Hữu này một ngày có ngày còn tu đến chín
because of suffering; there's nowhere else to
tại vì khổ quá rồi không còn chỗ nào nữa
go. Life is full of suffering, opening a shrine, serving as a medium, doing everything, fortune telling, all kinds of things. Now, only Buddhism remains, so there's nothing else to rely on. Therefore, I hope for this place, and that
cho nên trông mong chỗ này nó phải tinh
diligence will lead to a quick transformation.
tấn cho nên nó được chuyển hóa nhanh thế
Anyway, I wish all fellow practitioners all the best.
nhá rồi chúc C Quý đạo hữu mọi sự tốt
[music]
[âm nhạc]